Translator: tom carter
Reviewer: Bedirhan Cinar
A glimpse /ɡlɪmps 一瞥 /of teenage life in ancient Rome
It's March the 17th in A.D. 73.
We're visiting ancient Rome /rəʊm/
to watch the Liberalia,
an annual festival /ˈfɛstɪvəl/ that celebrates
the liberty of Rome's citizens.
We're looking in at a 17-year-old
named Lucius Popidius Secundus.
He's not from a poor family, but he lives
in the region known as the Subura,
a poorer neighborhood in Rome,
yet close to the center of the city.
(Gong)
The tenants /ˈtenənt/ of these
apartments are crammed /kræm 塞满/ in,
(Grunting /ɡrʌnt 呼噜声/)
which poses /pəʊz 造成/ considerable risk.
Fires are frequent and the smell of ash /æʃ 灰烬/
and smoke in the morning is not uncommon.
Lucius, who awoke at dawn,
has family duties to perform today.
(Cheering)
His 15-year-old brother is coming of age.
Half the children in ancient Rome
die before they reach adulthood /əˈdʌlthʊd/,
so this is a particularly
important milestone.
Lucius watches his brother
stand in his new toga /ˈtəʊɡə 托加长袍/
before the household shrine /ʃraɪn 神龛/
with its protective deities /ˈdeɪtɪ 女神/,
as he places his bulla /bʊlə 垂饰/,
a protective amulet /ˈæmjʊlət 护身符/,
in the shrine /ʃraɪn 神龛/ with a prayer of thanks.
The bulla /bʊlə 垂饰/ had worked.
It had protected him.
Unlike many others,
he had survived to become an adult.
At 17, Lucius has almost
completed his education.
He has learned to speak well,
make public speeches,
and how to read and write
both Latin /ˈlætɪn/ and Greek.
His father has taught him
the types of things
you can't learn in the classroom:
how to run,
how to swim,
and how to fight.
Lucius could choose, at 17,
to become a military tribune /ˈtrɪbjuːn 护民官/
and command soldiers
on the edge of the Empire.
But in other ways,
Lucius is still a child.
He's not trusted
to arrange business deals.
His father will take care
of that until he is 25.
And Dad will arrange Lucius' marriage
to a girl 10 years younger.
His dad has his eye on a family
with a 7-year-old daughter.
Back to the Liberalia.
As Lucius leaves with his family,
the shops are open as the population
goes about its business.
The streets are full
of itinerant /aɪˈtɪnərənt 流动性的/ traders selling trinkets /trɪŋkɪt 小饰品/
and people bustling /ˈbʌsəl 喧闹/ from place to place.
Large wagons /ˈwæɡən/ are not allowed
in the city until after the ninth hour
but the streets are still crowded.
Fathers and uncles
take the kids to the Forum /ˈfɔːrəm/ Augustus /ɔ:'gʌstəs/
to see statues of Rome's famous warriors
like Aeneas /i'ni:əs/, who led Rome's ancestors /ˈænsestər 祖先/,
the Trojans /trodʒənz/, to Italy.
And Romulus /rɑmjələs/, Rome's founder /创立者/.
And all the great generals of the Republic
from more than 100 years earlier.
Lovingly, we can imagine
fathers and guardians /gɑrdɪən 监护人/
with their now adult children
remembering stories of Rome's glory /ˈɡlɔːri/
and re-telling the good deeds /diːd 功绩/ and sayings
of the great men of the past:
lessons on how to live well,
and to overcome /ˌəʊvəˈkʌm 克服/ the follies /ˈfɒlɪ 愚蠢/ of youth / juːθ/.
There is a sense of history in this place,
relevant to their present.
Romans made an empire
without end in time and space.
(Thump /θʌmp 重击声/)
Rome was destined /ˈdestɪn 命注定/ to be
eternal /ɪˈtɜːnl/ through warfare.
Wars were a fact of life, even in A.D. 73.
There are campaigns /kæmˈpeɪn/ in the north
of England and into Scotland,
to the north of the River
Danube /'dænju:b 多瑙河/ into Romania,
and on the frontier
between Syria /ˈsɪriə/ and Iraq /ɪˈrɑːk/ to the east.
It's now the eighth hour --
time to head for the baths /bɑːθ/.
Lucius and his family head up
the Via Lata, the wide street,
to the Campus Martius,
and the enormous /ɪˈnɔːməs  庞大的/ Baths of Agrippa /ə'gripə/.
The family members leave
the clients and freedmen /被解放的奴隶/ outside,
and enter the baths with their peer group.
Baths would change from dark,
steamy /ˈstiːmi 蒸汽的/ rooms to light ones.
The Romans had perfected /ˈpɜːfɪkt/ window glass.
Everyone moves from the cold room
to the tepid /ˈtepɪd 微温的/ room
and to the very hot room.
(Man) Oops!
More than an hour later, the bathers leave
massaged /məˈsɑːʒ/, oiled,
(Whistling)
and have been scraped /skræp 拆毁/ down with a strigil /strɪdʒɪl 刮肤器 /
to remove the remaining dirt.
At the ninth hour, seven hours
after they left home,
the men return for a celebratory /ˌseləˈbreɪtəri/ dinner.
Dinner is an intimate /ˈɪntɪmɪt 亲密的/ affair,
with nine people
reclining  /rɪˈklaɪn 使斜靠/ around the low table.
Slaves attend to their every need
if the diners, through gestures /ˈdʒɛstʃə 手势/,
demand more food and wine.
As the day closes, we can hear
the rumble /ˈrʌmbl 隆隆声/ of wagons /ˈwæɡən/ outside.
The clients and freedmen,
with a meal of robust /ˈwæɡən/
-- if inferior /ɪnˈfɪərɪə 低等的 部下/ -- food inside them,
shuffle /ˈʃʌfəl 拖着脚步走/ off to the now tepid /ˈtepɪd 微温的/ baths
before returning
to their apartment blocks.
Back at Lucius' house,
the drinking continues into the night.
Lucius and his stepbrother /ˈstepbrʌðə 异父之兄弟/
don't look too well.
A slave stands by in case
either of them needs to vomit /ˈvɒmɪt 呕吐/.
With hindsight /ˈhaɪndˌsaɪt 事后聪明/, we know Lucius' future.
In 20 years' time, the Emperor Vespasian's /ves'peiʒiən/
youngest son, Domitian /'də'miʃən/, as emperor,
will enact /ɪˈnækt 颁布/ a reign /reɪn 支配/ of terror. / terə 恐怖/
Will Lucius survive?
(Drums /drʌm 鼓 鼓声/)